MOHAMAD LAWAND

Manchester, UK ↑
+447879257622 ↓
mohamad.lawand@outlook.com
mlawand in
https://mohamadlawand.com
https://bit.ly/2MiAAQi



PROFESSIONAL SUMMARY

A determined and forward-thinking **Technical Architect** with 13+ years of experience, working across a wide range of industries, from financial institutes to government entities. Proactive and adaptable, specializing in SaaS and Blockchain technologies across multiple platforms; with a strong understanding and deep practical experience in developing sustainable, secure and long-lasting business applications. Developed applications and provided tangible and measurable results for clients; from process automation, accessibility, integration, scalability, security and availability. With a wide portfolio of developing innovative solutions through advanced architectures.



SKILLS

- Leading end-to-end digital transformation
- SaaS Cloud Platform Development
- Business Process Re-Engineering
- Blockchain Development
- Enterprise Application Development & Integration
- System Architecture
- Team Management

- Project Management
- Product Life Cycle Management -Agile/Scrum
- User Experience
- Online Security and Testing
- Microsoft Stack
- System Integration
- Cloud Architecture



EXPERIENCE

Sage April 2021 – Present

Sage is the market leader for integrated accounting, payroll, and payment systems, supporting the ambition of the world's entrepreneurs.

Technical Architect

Responsible for the designing and upgrading of exciting, industry-leading Payroll applications. Facilitating production releases frequently to help push its payroll product to new market like Canada, United States and South Africa.

 Revamping the development pipeline: upgrading and changing the DevOps pipelines to streamline the deployment process across different environment and removing a lot of the blockers that Devs and QA are facing on day to day.

- Service Integrations: Upgrading an existing application from a Monolith to a Macro Service structure, created a roadmap highlighting what needs to be done from a technical, DevOps pipeline and integration point of view. And we started on the implementations.
- Go To Market Ready: reviewed the entire platform we are working to make sure we are go to market ready, communicated with the cloud team and different services to make sure we have all of the right implementations, configs.

Tech Stack: .Net core, Azure, Docker, Terraform

Interact Intranet Feb 2020 – April 2021

Interact is a global enterprise software company that serves intranet software to millions of users across the globe. Organizations thrive when people are informed and connected. For more than 15 years, Interact's team of experts have worked side-by-side with customers all over the world to deliver a complete intranet solution that brings their workforces together to communicate and collaborate.

Interact has offices in Manchester and New York and operates across the whole of the US and Canada, EMEA, and Australia.

Technical Manager | Lead Developer

Responsible for the design and development of exciting, industry-leading business features within the Interact platform. Facilitating production releases frequently to help push company expansion throughout the UK and US.

- **Solution Architecture:** Design and implement the development of new features and upgrades into the main product.
- **Lead Development**: Built an integration platform with 3rd party systems, enabled SSO to different services with platform multitenancy. Enhanced the REST API interface with JWT integrations.
- Team Management: Successfully managed and led cross-functional teams of developers. Created and guided team to adhere to specific coding standards. Completed code review and managed the team tasks and deliverables. Met deadlines to provide time sensitive customer and operational feedback to clients.

Tech Stack: .Net Framework, .Net core, AWS, Docker

Miza September 2019 – Jan 2020

Launched in 2017 as a centralized system for buying and paying bills and other transfers electronically in Libya, Miza facilitates and speeds up various payments to individuals, banks, companies and the government sector, and continues to develop new services that include all payments. One for all payments especially in this difficult period with no cash available.

Senior Solution Architect/Lead Developer

Led the application development, for A2F (access to finance) platform, which is a Supply Chain Financing Solution.

- Solution Architecture: Refined and built on top of current application architecture to make the solution cloud ready and scalable. Introduced container architecture and Microservices for certain part of the solutions.
- Lead Development: Laid the foundations for the backend/frontend development. Create the application cloud infrastructure with CI/CD pipelines using Azure Container Management and Docker.
- Blockchain Development: Started creating the blockchain development framework using private blockchain (Corda R3). Defined the architecture and the development framework for the smart contracts.
- **Team Management**: Started building the development team and managed 3 developers working on the frontend and the backends.

Tech Stack: .Net core, Azure, Corda, Kotlin, Docker, Kubernetes

Equitativa

May 2019 – September 2019

Leading regional asset management company that focuses on managing real estate investment trusts (REITs). The holding group offers innovative risk-adjusted, income generating financial products that cater to institutional and retail investors.

Blockchain Architect

Led the Blockchain development, as a blockchain architect, I worked closely with the property management to get a better understanding about the assets and property management.

- **Blockchain Development**: Transformed some of the legacy application to managing property ownership and KYC into the blockchain. Created an ERC20 and ERC721 tokens with airdrop functionalities to certain clientele based on predefined business cases.
- **Team Management**: Helped the backend development team understand blockchain fundamentals and concepts. Trained some team members on Solidity and smart contract management.

Tech Stack: Java, Solidity, C++

Mentor Global Consultants

July 2014 – May 2019

A management consulting firm that helps organizations to improve performance and reach their full potential through consulting services, supported by digital solutions.

Senior Application Architect | Development Team Lead

Responsible for managing the technology team and technology service line offering. As lead application architect, I work closely with Mentor GC Engagement Managers to establish a product life cycle and to analyze clients' business needs in order to design, develop, implement and support state of the art solution based on the latest technology trends and requirements.

- Leading end-to-end digital transformation: Spearheaded the design and implementation of an online learning management system to manage all training activities within a leading bank in the UAE. As a result, the bank was able to quickly roll out mandatory courses for its entire workforce and deliver 5,000 e-learning courses in 2017, surpassing workshops and constituting 67% of total training sessions. The system has managed 6,000 workshops since its launch, and processes roughly 300 workshop/e-learning requests daily. The bank is now able to provide more workshops faster and with less effort, and meet its annual employee training quota of 5 training man-days.
- SaaS Cloud Platform Development: Successfully built a comprehensive SaaS solution designed to centralize and streamline talent development, bringing together all users, processes, content and data. With many customized applications, it facilitates competency management, assessment and career planning, and provides easy access to learning content and activities. The system is built to simultaneously hold up to 50,000 users with no loss in performance. The SaaS platform was hosted under Microsoft Azure to ensure high availability and configured with local redundancy.
- SaaS Cloud Platform Development: The application is SaaS based to serve different clients across different regions and geographies. Using Microsoft Azure cloud services the application has been using across Mena and the US without any latency and with high availability.
- **Blockchain Development**: Pioneered the development of an online platform that brings together a worldwide community that is inspired by the potential of technology and passionate about learning. Enabled and secured through blockchain technology, the platform connects users to learning, mentoring and employment opportunities in order to achieve a fulfilling livelihood in technology related professions.
- **Team Management:** Successfully managed and led cross-functional teams from development to Quality Assurance. Created and made team adhere to specific coding standards. Met deadlines to provide time sensitive customer and operational feedback to clients.
- Business Process Re-engineering: Introduced a knowledge management portal for the employees of a local bank to enhance knowledge transfer and increase employee's awareness of bank products, policies and procedures. This enabled the staff to perform their duties and work more efficiently with the ability to make online requests for assistance with internal product owners.

Tech Stack: .Net core, Azure, Solidity, Docker

Born interactive

April 2014 – September 2014

A 20 year-old independent Integrated Communication Agency dedicated to offering creative, innovative, state-of-the-art digital and interactive communication solutions and experiences, to meet the evolving needs of local, regional, and global institutional and corporate clients.

Senior Web and Mobile Developer

Led the Windows Phone development team, as a senior web and mobile developer, I worked closely with the project management team to enhance the client's current mobile applications and update the application to latest version of Windows Phone.

- System Architecture: Enhanced an existing Windows Phone 8.1 applications, to allow radio and podcast streaming of Kurdish, Arabic stations. Upgraded the architecture of the application in order to integrate a market place with a payment gateway integration (Paypal and NetCommerce). This gave users the ability to access their paid content from their mobile device and the online store.
- User Experience: Developed a Facebook application for the Lebanese Ministry of Tourism, allowing users to share their own pictures and videos of the Lebanese landscapes and views to promote tourism. The application was built with a user-friendly interface in order to encourage engagement.

Tech Stack: .Net Framework, Windows Phone, C#, SQLite

Ubanquity LTD

January 2013 – April 2014

A privately held Irish-based FinTech specialized in offering ubiquitous and cutting-edge products and solutions to banks and financial institutions, catering to the next generation of customers, in an everchanging environment.

Windows Phone Developer

Played an integral part of the mobile development team. I was responsible for the Windows Phone Platform; focusing on a banking application that promotes an innovative and intuitive way of banking allowing the user to access financial services with minimal navigation.

- **System Integration:** Successfully collaborated with the API and Middleware teams to enhance the application architecture, and enable offline features; giving the application a competitive advantage in the market. Some of the project highlights include the following:
 - The application was adopted by a bank in Jordan
 - The application was adopted by 2 banks in Lebanon
 - Created client reward system which were adopted by all other platforms (IOS, Android and BB10)
 - Mentored some team members on the UWP in order to import the application to the Windows Store.
 - Created the basis of the Windows Store application and managed a team of developers who were responsible for continuing developing the application.

Tech Stack: .Net Framework, C#, C++

Cleartag International

May 2010 – May 2013

Cleartag is a web design and development agency in Lebanon, Dubai and Saudi Arabia. *Cleartag* is a provider of digital solutions in the MENA region.

Web Developer

Responsible for the development of websites for clients and building and maintaining an interactive kiosk application for a leading bank in Lebanon.

- Enterprise Application Development & Integration: Developed the main Windows Communication Foundation (WCF) and Data Layer for a digital self-service branch for a leading bank. The objective of the self-service application is to create a comfortable and user-friendly banking experience for customers. The application allows for products to be easily accessible, visualized, and explained through an enhanced communication channel. The main communication layer is built on a secure peer to peer network which enables the application to communicate with the bank customer database and the application database to create the personalized experience for each customer.
- SaaS Cloud Platform Development: Developed an online marketplace that offers users convenience at its best. Through its different and innovative sections, users will have the ability to shop & ship from the US, benefit from special hot deals by different Lebanese merchants. The application had 3 different backends to manage the application (Vendors, Admin and Shipments providers).
- Maintenance, Change and Incident Management:
 - Maintained and enhanced a Banking Application used within an international bank in Lebanon used for check clearing and IATA checking, as well as integrating with the latest check reading and printing peripherals.
 - Optimized the general performance of banking cards for a leading bank, by optimizing the data layer that communicate with 2 different databases; Oracle and SQL server. Enhancing the security of the sites by eliminating security holes found in the systems. As well as fixing issues related to the FINI (SOAP) System.

Tech Stack: .Net Framework, PHP, Java



EDUCATION

Bachelor of Arts | Hariri Canadian University

2006 - 2011

Business Administration/ Business Computing Major

Additional Professional Development

- Certified Ethical Hacker by EC Council V8
- Certified Swift Level 2 from Cambridge Certification Authority
- Completed Developing Solutions for Microsoft Azure (AZ-204)
- Certified Project Management **PRINCE2 Foundation**



ACHIEVEMENTS

• Nominated to be a mentor at the EOSIO Hackathons in both Hong Kong and Australia

- Selected from a pool of 4,000+ applicants to be part of the second cohort of the Antler Co-Founder Accelerator program in Singapore
- Participated in IOST Blockchain Market Penetration Strategy
- Grew a tech YouTube channel to more than 1500 subscribers in 7 months, teaching C#, Asp.Net Core, Azure, Angular and DevOps



TECHNICAL PROFICIENCIES & FUNCTIONAL EXPERTISE

- SaaS application development
- Project Management
- Blockchain (EOSIO, Corda, Solidity, Truffle, Hyperledger)
- C#, C++, Java, JavaScript and PHP
- Web Development (ASP.Net & .Net Core, Angular, VueJs)
- Mobile Development (Cordova, Xamarin, Swift)
- Service Development (WCF)
- Desktop Development (Win Forms, WPF, UWP)
- Database development. (MSSQL, MySQL, Azure SQL DB)



LANGUAGES

Arabic – Native Speaker

English – Full professional proficiency

French - Full professional proficiency

Spanish – Currently learning